About 12 years ago,
قبل حوالي 12 سنة ،
I gave up my career in banking
تركت عملي في مجال الخدمات المصرفية
to try to make the world a safer place.
في محاولة مني لجعل العالم مكاناً آمناً .
This involved a journey into national and global advocacy
وشمل ذلك رحلة دعم وطنية وعالمية
and meeting some of the most extraordinary people in the world.
ومقابلة بعض من أكثر الناس النوابغ والخارقين في العالم .
In the process, I became a civil society diplomat.
وفي هذه العملية ،أصبحت دبلوماسية للمجتمع المدني .
Civil society diplomats do three things:
يقوم دبلوماسيو المجتمع المدني بثلاثة أشياء :
They voice the concerns of the people,
يعبرون عن هموم الناس،
are not pinned down by national interests,
التي لم تكن من ضمن الاهتمامات الوطنية،
and influence change through citizen networks,
وإحداث تغيرات على مستوى المواطنين،
not only state ones.
وليس على مستوى الدولة فقط .
And if you want to change the world, we need more of them.
واذا أردت أن تغير العالم ، فإننا نحتاج إلى الكثير منهم .
But many people still ask,
ولكن العديد من الناس مازال يسألون،
"Can civil society really make a big difference?
هل من الممكن حقاّ للمجتمع المدني أن يحدث فارقاً كبيراً ؟
Can citizens influence and shape national and global policy?"
هل بإمكان المواطنين أن يشكلوا ويؤثروا على السياسة المحلية والعالمية ؟
I never thought I would ask myself these questions,
لم أكن أعتقد أبدا أنه من الممكن أن أسأل نفسي مثل هذه الأسئلة،
but here I am to share some lessons
ولكني هنا الآن لأنشر بعضاً من هذه الدروس
about two powerful civil society movements that I've been involved in.
عن حركتين قويتين من المجتمع المدني التي شاركت فيهما.
They are in issues that I'm passionate about:
هي قضايا لدي شغف بها :
gun control and drug policy.
التحكم في السلاح وسياسة المخدرات.
And these are issues that matter here.
وهذه هي القضايا التي تهمنا هنا.
Latin America is ground zero for both of them.
أمريكا اللاتينية هي نقطة البداية لكليهما.
For example, Brazil --
وعلى سبيل المثال ،البرازيل--
this beautiful country hosting TEDGlobal has the world's ugliest record.
هذا البلد الجميل الذي يستضيف مؤتمر TEDGlobal لديه أسوء سجل عالمي في هذه الجرائم.
We are the number one champion in homicidal violence.
فنحن رقم 1عالميا في العنف القاتل.
One in every 10 people killed around the world is a Brazilian.
1 من كل 10 قتلى حول العالم برازيلي.
This translates into over 56,000 people
بمعنى آخر ما يزيد عن 56,000 برازيلي
dying violently each year.
يموتون بسبب العنف كل عام.
Most of them are young, black boys dying by guns.
معظمهم من الشباب،أو الأطفال ذوي البشرة السوداء ممن يموتون بالسلاح.
Brazil is also one of the world's largest consumers of drugs,
البرازيل هي أيضاً واحدة من أكثر دول العالم استهلاكاً للمخدرات،
and the War on Drugs has been especially painful here.
والحرب على المخدرات كانت مؤلمة هنا.
Around 50 percent of the homicides in the streets in Brazil
حوالي 50% من جرائم القتل التي تحدث في شوارع البرازيل
are related to the War on Drugs.
مرتبطة بحرب المخدرات.
The same is true for about 25 percent of people in jail.
والحقيقة الأخرى أن 25% من البرازيليين موجودون في السجون.
And it's not just Brazil that is affected by the twin problems of guns and drugs.
وليست البرازيل وحدها التي تعاني من مشاكل المخدرات والسلاح.
Virtually every country and city across Central and South America is in trouble.
ففعلياً كل دولة أو مدينة في أمريكا الجنوبية أو الوسطى تعاني من هذه المشاكل.
Latin America has nine percent of the world's population,
تشكل أمريكا اللاتينية ما نسبته 9% من سكان العالم،
but 25 percent of its global violent deaths.
ولكنها تشكل 25 % من قتلى العنف حول العالم.
These are not problems we can run away from.
فلا يمكننا أن نغض الطرف عن مثل هذه المشاكل.
I certainly could not.
أنا شخصيأ بالتأكيد لا يمكنني ذلك .
So the first campaign I got involved with started here in 2003
لذا فإن أول حملة اشتركت بها بدأت هنا في عام 2003
to change Brazil's gun law
لتغير قانون السلاح في البرازيل
and to create a program to buy back weapons.
ولإقامة برنامج لإعادة شراء الأسلحة.
In just a few years,
في غضون عدة سنوات.
we not only changed national legislation
لم نقم بتغيرالتشريع الوطني فحسب
that made it much more difficult for civilians to buy a gun,
والذي جعل عملية شراء الأسلحة من طرف المدنين أكثر صعوبة،
but we collected and destroyed almost half a million weapons.
ولكننا قمنا أيضاً بجمع وتدمير ما يقارب نصف مليون قطعة سلاح.
This was one of the biggest buyback programs in history --
لقد كانت هذه أكبر عملية إعادة شراء في التاريخ --
(Applause) --
(تصفيق )
but we also suffered some setbacks.
ولكننا عانينا أيضأ من الكثير من النكسات.
We lost a referendum to ban gun sales to civilians in 2005.
فقد خسرنا في استفتاءعام لحظر بيع السلاح للمدنينين في عام 2005 .
The second initiative was also home-grown,
المبادرة الثانية كانت محلية أيضاً،
but is today a global movement to reform the international drug control regime.
ولكن اليوم هناك حركة عالمية لإصلاح النظام الدولي لمراقبة المخدرات.
I am the executive coordinator
وأنا منسقة تنفيذية
of something called the Global Commission on Drug Policy.
في ما يسمى اللجنة العالمية لسياسة المخدرات.
The commission is a high-level group
اللجنة هي مجموعة رفيعة المستوى
of global leaders brought together to identify more humane
من قادة عالميين يعملون مع بعضهم لتحديد مفاهيم إنسانية أكثر
and effective approaches to the issue of drugs.
ومقاربات فعالة تتعلق بقضية المخدرات.
Since we started in 2008, the taboo on drugs is broken.
ومنذ بدايةعملنا في عام 2008 فإن قيود المخدرات قد كسرت .
Across the Americas, from the US and Mexico to Colombia and Uruguay,
وعبر الأمريكيتين،من الولايات المتحدة والمكسيك ،إلى كولومبيا والأرغواي،
change is in the air.
فإن التغيير بدأ يلوح في الأفق.
But rather than tell you the whole story about these two movements,
ولكن بدلاً من أن أخبركم بالقصة الكاملة عن هاتين الحركتين،
I just want to share with you four key insights.
أود فقط أن أشارككم بأربع أفكار رئيسية.
I call them lessons to change the world.
أسميهم دروس لتغير العالم.
There are certainly many more,
وهناك بالتأكيد دروس كثيرةغيرها،
but these are the ones that stand out to me.
ولكن هذه الأفكار هي الأهم بالنسبة لي.
So the first lesson is:
فالدرس الأول هو :
Change and control the narrative.
قم بالتغيير والتحكم في القصة.
It may seem obvious,
ربما يبدو ذلك واضحاً،
but a key ingredient to civil society diplomacy
ولكن العنصر الأساسي في دبلوماسية المجمتع المدني
is first changing and then controlling the narrative.
هو التغيير أولاً،ومن ثم التحكم بالقصة .
This is something that veteran politicians understand,
وهذا الشيء مفهوم بالنسبة للسياسين المحنكين،
but that civil society groups generally do not do very well.
ولكن مجموعات المجتمع المدني لا تقوم ذلك بشكل حيد .
In the case of drug policy,
وفيما يتعلق بسياسة المخدرات،
our biggest success has been to change the discussion
فإن أكبر نجاح لنا أننا قمنا بتغير طريقة المناقشة
away from prosecuting a War on Drugs
من كونها استمراراً بالحرب على المخدرات
to putting people's health and safety first.
إلى الاهتمام بصحة الناس وسلامتهم في المقام الأول.
In a cutting-edge report we just launched in New York,
وفي التقرير النهائي الذي أطلقناه لتونا في نيويورك،
we also showed that the groups benefiting most from this $320 billion market
أظهرنا أيضاً أن الجهات المستفيدة من ال 320 مليار دولار في سوق المخدرات
are criminal gangs and cartels.
هم عصابات المجرمين.
So in order to undermine the power and profit of these groups,
لذا من أجل إضعاف سلطة والتقليل من أرباح هذه المجموعات،
we need to change the conversation.
علينا أن نغير طريقة الحوار .
We need to make illegal drugs legal.
وعلينا أن نجعل المخدرات غير القانونية قانونية.
But before I get you too excited,
ولكن قبل ان أجعلكم تفرحون جدا،
I don't mean drugs should be a free-for-all.
فأنا هنا لا أعني بأن المخدرات يجب أن تتوفر بشكل مجاني للجميع.
What I'm talking about, and what the Global Commission advocates for
ولكن ما أقصده وما تسعى إليه اللجنة العالمية
is creating a highly regulated market,
هو خلق سوق منظم للغاية،
where different drugs would have different degrees of regulation.
حيث أن أنواع المخدرات المختلفة ستكون لها درجات مختلفة من التنظيم.
As for gun control, we were successful in changing,
أما بالنسبة للسيطرة على السلاح فلقد نجحنا بالتغيير،
but not so much in controlling, the narrative.
ولكن لم يكن نجاحاً مبهراً في في التحكم في القصة .
And this brings me to my next lesson:
وهذا يقودني إلى الدرس الثاني :
Never underestimate your opponents.
لا تقلل من شأن خصمك أبداً.
If you want to succeed in changing the world,
إذا أردت فعلاً أن تنجح في تغيير العالم،
you need to know who you're up against.
فعليك أن تعرف من هو ضدك.
You need to learn their motivations and points of view.
وعليك أن تعرف ما هي دوافعهم ووجهات نظرهم.
In the case of gun control,
فيما يتعلق بالتحكم في السلاح،
we really underestimated our opponents.
فنحن بالفعل قللنا من شأن خصومنا.
After a very successful gun-collection program,
وبعد برنامج جمع الأسلحة الناجح بامتياز
we were elated.
كنا سعداء للغاية .
We had support from 80 percent of Brazilians,
وحصلنا على دعم من أكثر من 80% من البرازيليين،
and thought that this could help us win the referendum
واعتقدنا بأن ذلك سيساعدنا كثيراً في الاستفتاء
to ban gun sales to civilians.
بحظر بيع الأسلحة للمدنيين.
But we were dead wrong.
ولكننا أسأنا التقدير.
During a televised 20-day public debate,
وخلال مناقشة عامة متلفزة لمدة 20 يوماً،
our opponent used our own arguments against us.
استخدم خصومنا مناقاشاتنا الحادة كسلاح ضدنا.
We ended up losing the popular vote.
وفي النهاية خسرنا التصويت الشعبي.
It was really terrible.
كان ذلك فظيعا حقاً.
The National Rifle Association -- yes, the American NRA --
الرابطة الوطنية الأمريكية للسلاح نعم الأمريكية المعروفة باختصار NRA--
came to Brazil.
جاءت إلى البرازيل.
They inundated our campaign with their propaganda,
لقد غطت على حملتنا بإشاعاتها،
that as you know,
وهذا كما تعرفون،
links the right to own guns to ideas of freedom and democracy.
يربط حق امتلاك السلاح بأفكار الحرية والديمقراطية.
They simply threw everything at us.
ببساطة رموا كل شيء علينا.
They used our national flag,
لقد استخدموا علمنا الوطني،
our independence anthem.
ونشيد الاستقلال الخاص بنا .
They invoked women's rights
لقد تذرعوا بحقوق المرأة
and misused images of Mandela, Tiananmen Square, and even Hitler.
وأساءوا استخدام صور مانديلا ، ساحة تيانانمن، وحتى صور هتلر.
They won by playing with people's fears.
لقدربحوا من خلال اللعب على وتر خوف الناس .
In fact, guns were almost completely ignored in their campaign.
في الواقع تم تجاهل موضوع الأسلحة بشكل شبه كامل في حملتهم.
Their focus was on individual rights.
وكان تركيزهم على الحقوق الفردية .
But I ask you,
ولكن أريد أن أسألكم،
which right is more important,
ما هو الحق الأهم،
the right to life
حق الحياة
or the right to have a gun that takes life away?
أم الحق بامتلاك السلاح الذي ينهي الحياة ؟
(Applause)
(تصفيق )
We thought people would vote in defense of life,
لقد اعتقدنا بأن الناس سيصوتون للدفاع عن الحياة،
but in a country with a recent past of military dictatorship,
ولكن في بلد يعاني من الديكتاتورية العسكرية منذ الماضي القريب،
the anti-government message of our opponents resonated,
فإن الرسالة المناهضة للحكومة من من معارضينا كان لها صدى،
and we were not prepared to respond.
ولم نكن جاهزين للرد عليهم.
Lesson learned.
تعلمنا الدرس.
We've been more successful in the case of drug policy.
لقد كنا أكثر نجاحاً فيما يتعلق بسياسة المخدرات .
If you asked most people 10 years ago if an end to the War on Drugs was possible,
لو سألت معظم الناس قبل 10 سنوات هل نهاية الحرب على المخدرات ممكنة،
they would have laughed.
لكانوا قد ضحكوا.
After all, there are huge military police prisons
على كل حال،هناك عدد ضخم من سجون الشرطة العسكرية
and financial establishments benefiting from this war.
ومؤسسات مالية مستفيدة من هذه الحرب.
But today, the international drug control regime is starting to crumble.
ولكن في هذه االأيام،بدأ نظام المراقبة الدولي على المخدرات بالانهيار.
Governments and civil societies are experimenting with new approaches.
تجرب المجتمعات المدنية والحكومات أساليب جديدة.
The Global Commission on Drug Policy
اللجنه العالمية لسياسة المخدرات
really knew its opposition,
تعرف حقاً معارضيها،
and rather than fighting them,
وبدلا من مواجهتهم،
our chair -- former Brazilian President Fernando Henrique Cardoso --
فإن رئيسنا-- الرئيس البرازيلي السابق فرناندو هنريك كاردوسو--
reached out to leaders from across the political spectrum,
مد يده إلى قادة من مختلف ألوان الطيف السياسي،
from liberals to conservatives.
من الليبراليين إلى المحافظين .
This high level group agreed to honestly discuss
وافقت هذه المجموعة رفيعة المستوى على المناقشة بكل صراحة
the merits and flaws of drug policies.
حول مزايا وعيوب سياسات المخدرات.
It was this reasoned, informed and strategic discussion
لقد كان نقاشا استراتيجيا مقنعا
that revealed the sad truth about the War on Drugs.
كشف حقيقة مؤلمة عن الحرب على المخدرات.
The War on Drugs has simply failed across every metric.
ببساطه الحرب على المخدرات فشلت بكل المقاييس.
Drugs are cheaper and more available than ever,
فالمخدرات أصبحت أرخص ومتاحة بشكل أكثر من ذي قبل.
and consumption has risen globally.
وزاد استهلاكها بشكل عالمي .
But even worse,
والأسوء من ذلك،
it also generated massive negative unintended consequences.
أنها أنتجت عواقب وخيمة كبيرة.
It is true that some people have made these arguments before,
وصحيح أن بعض الناس قدموا هذه الحجج من قبل،
but we've made a difference
ولكننا أحدثنا تغييرا
by anticipating the arguments of our opponents
من خلال إحباط حجج خصومنا
and by leveraging powerful voices
ومن خلال الإستفادة من الأصوات القوية
that a few years ago would probably have resisted change.
التي من المرجح أنها كانت لتقاوم هذا التغيير قبل عدة سنوات.
Third lesson: Use data to drive your argument.
الدرس الثالث استخدم المعلومات لتدعم حجتك .
Guns and drugs are emotive issues,
السلاح والمخدرات قضايا عاطفية،
and as we've painfully learned in the gun referendum campaign in Brazil,
وكما تعلمنا بألم من حملة الاستفتاء على السلاح التي قمنا بها بالبرازيل،
sometimes it's impossible to cut through the emotions
أنه في بعض الأحيان من المستحيل أن تمنع شيئا متعلقا بالعواطف
and get to the facts.
وتوصلنا لهذه الحقائق.
But this doesn't mean that we shouldn't try.
ولكن هذا لا يعني أنه ليس علينا أن نحاول .
Until quite recently,
حتى وقت قريب جداً،
we simply didn't know how many Brazilians were killed by guns.
لم نكن نعرف ببساطة عدد البرازيليين الذين قتلوا بالسلاح.
Amazingly, it was a local soap opera called "Mulheres Apaixonadas" --
ومن المذهل أن مسلسلا محليا اسمه "مولهيرز ابايكسوناداس "--
or "Women in Love" --
أو" إمرأة في الحب "--
that kicked off Brazil's national gun control campaign.
أطلق حملة محلية للسيطرة على السلاح في البرازيل.
In one highly viewed episode,
ففي إحدى حلقاته ذات المشاهدات العالية،
a soap opera lead actress was killed by a stray bullet.
تم قتل بطلة المسلسل برصاصة طائشة .
Brazilian grannies and housewives were outraged,
فغضبت الجدات وربات البيوت البرازيليات لمشاهدة هذا المشهد،
and in a case of art imitating life,
وبما أن الفن يعكس الحياة،
this episode also included footage of a real gun control march
فقد شملت هذه الحلقه أيضاً لقطات من مسيرة عرض الأسلحة
that we had organized right here,
التي نظمناها هنا،
outside in Copacabana Beach.
خارجاً في شاطئ كوباكابانا.
The televised death and march had a huge impact on public opinion.
الوفاة المتلفزة والمسيرة كان لها تأثير كبير على الرأي العام .
Within weeks, our national congress approved the disarmament bill
وفي غضون أسابيع ،وافق المؤتمر الوطني لدينا على مشروع قانون نزع السلاح
that had been languishing for years.
الذي كان ضعيفأ منذ سنوات.
We were then able to mobilize data
وكنا قادرين بعد ذلك على تعئبة البيانات
to show the successful outcomes of the change in the law
لإظهار النتائج الناجحة الناتجة عن التغيير في هذا القانون
and gun collection program.
وبرنامج جمع الأسلحة.
Here is what I mean:
وهذا ما أقصده هنا :
We could prove that in just one year,
لقد أثبتنا بأنه في خلال عام واحد فقط،
we saved more than 5,000 lives.
حمينا أكثر من 5,000 روح من القتل.
(Applause)
(تصفيق )
And in the case of drugs,
وفيما يتعلق بمشكل المخدرات،
in order to undermine this fear and prejudice that surrounds the issue,
فمن أجل القضاء على هذا الخوف والتحيز الملازم لهذه القضية،
we managed to gather and present data that shows that today's drug policies
فقد تمكنا من جمع البيانات الحالية التي تظهر بأن سياسات المخدرات هذه الأيام
cause much more harm than drug use per se,
تسبب أضراراً أكثر من استخدام المخدرات بحد ذاتها،
and people are starting to get it.
فبدأ الناس بتفهم هذه الأمور.
My fourth insight is:
وفكرتي الرابعة هي :
Don't be afraid to bring together odd bedfellows.
لا تخف أبدا ً من أن تجمع المتحالفين غريبي الأطوار.
What we've learned in Brazil --
ما تعلمناه في البرازيل--
and this doesn't only apply to my country --
وهذا لا يمكن تطبيقه فقط في بلدي--
is the importance of bringing diverse and eclectic folks together.
هو أهمية جلب الناس معاً بطريقة متنوعة أو منتقاة.
If you want to change the world,
إذا أردت أن تغير العالم،
it helps to have a good cross-section of society on your side.
فمن المفيد ،أن يكون لديك شريحة كبيرة من المجتمع تقف بجانبك.
In both the case of guns and drugs,
فييما يخص السلاح والمخدرات كليهما،
we brought together a wonderful mix of people.
لقد جمعنا مزيجا جميلا من الناس.
We mobilized the elite and got huge support from the media.
لقد قمنا بإقناع النخبة من المجمتع وحصلنا على دعم كبير من الإعلام .
We gathered the victims, human rights champions, cultural icons.
لقد جمعنا الضحايا وأبطال حقوق الانسان والرموز الثقافية .
We also assembled the professional classes --
وقمنا أيضاً بجمع الطبقات المهنية--
doctors, lawyers, academia and more.
من أطباء ،ومحامين ،وأكاديمين ،وغيرهم .
What I've learned over the last years
ما تعلمته خلال هذه السنوات الماضية
is that you need coalitions of the willing and of the unwilling to make change.
بأنك بحاجة إلى تحالف من الراغبين وغيرالراغبين في تحقيق التغيير.
In the case of drugs,
وفيما يتعلق بالمخدرات،
we needed libertarians, anti-prohibitionists, legalizers,
نحن بحاجهة إلى ليبرالين،ومناهضين للحظر،ومشرعين،
and liberal politicians.
وسياسيين ليراليين.
They may not agree on everything;
ربما لن يوافقوا على كل شيء،
in fact, they disagree on almost everything.
في الحقيقة هم يعارضون معظم الأشياء .
But the legitimacy of the campaign is based on their diverse points of view.
ولكن شرعية الحملة تستند على اختلاف وجهات نظرهم.
Over a decade ago,
منذ أكثر من عقد من الزمن،
I had a comfortable future working for an investment bank.
كان لدي مستقبل مريح حيث كنت أعمل في بنك استثماري .
I was as far removed from the world of civil society diplomacy
كنت بعيدة عن عالم دبلوماسية المجمتع المدني
as you can imagine.
كما يمكنكم أن تتخيلوا.
But I took a chance.
ولكنني حصلت على فرصة.
I changed course,
وغيرت المسار،
and on the way, I helped to create social movements
وبالسير في هذا الطريق،ساعدت على على خلق حركات اجتماعية
that I believe have made some parts of the world safer.
التي أعتقد أنها جعلت بعض مناطق العالم أكثر أماناً .
Each and every one of us has the power to change the world.
كل واحد منا لديه القدرة على تغيير العالم .
No matter what the issue, and no matter how hard the fight,
بغض النظرعن القضية،أو صعوبة المواجهة،
civil society is central to the blueprint for change.
فالمجتمع المدني هو المركزلخطط التغيير.
Thank you.
شكراً .
(Applause)
(تصفيق)